Office of the Dean, School of Medicine Records UA186
Digital Collections and Archives, Tufts University
Office of the Dean, School of Medicine Records
1954 -- 2014
Digital Collections and Archives, Tufts University
School of Medicine
Office of the Dean of the School of Medicine
UA186
12.0 Linear Feet 10 boxes and one oversized folder.
4 Digital Object(s)
Arrangement
This collection is arranged in five series: Liaison Committee on Medical Education (LCME) accreditation records; Departmental annual reports; Meeting minutes; Subject files; and Unprocessed accessions.
Biographical / Historical
The Medical School and Dental School were jointly administered by one Dean until 1914, when the Office of the Vice-Dean was created in the Medical School. The Dental School added its own Vice-Dean in 1915, and then in 1917 appointed its own Dean, thereby separating the administration of the two schools. The Medical School was renamed the School of Medicine in 1954 when Tufts College became Tufts University.
Subsequently, the Office of the Dean has been involved in numerous transitional processes for the continuously expanding School of Medicine. Particularly, Deans have been involved in the creation and administration of the Tufts Medical Center as it has gradually acquired additional facilities and resources in the downtown area.
The Office of the Dean of the School of Medicine administers the academic departments, student services, and facilities of the Tufts University School of Medicine, and supervises the School's teaching and research activities. The Office of the Dean performs a variety of tasks to fulfill its larger objectives, such as recruitment of new faculty and strategic and financial planning.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains records, reports, and meeting minutes created by the Office of the Dean, School of Medicine.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection contains some restricted material. Restrictions related to specific material are listed in the detailed contents list.
Administration and Governance -- Planning, evaluation, policies & procedures; Administration and Governance -- Accreditation; Research and Research Administration; Facilities
- Liaison Committee on Medical Education (LCME) accreditation records, 1954 -- 2014; UA186.001; 4.8 Linear Feet
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains records created during the LCME accreditation process, including planning documents, self-studies, reports, recommendations, and revisit reports.
  Arrangement
  This series is arranged chronologically.
  Conditions Governing Access
  20 years from date of creation.
  - Accreditation records, 1954 -- 1986; UA186.001.001 (Box 1)
    Contains LCME materials from 1954, 1963, 1971, 1977, 1980, 1983, and 1985-1986.
  - Accreditation records, 1987 -- 1997; UA186.001.002 (Box 2)
    Includes LCME materials from the 1987 accreditation revisit, the 1995 TUSM Strategic Plan Draft Report, and August 20, 1996 LCME Secretariat interim visit.
  - Accreditation records, 1999 -- 2006; UA186.001.003 (Box 3)
    Contains the 1999 LCME Survey Report, 1999 TUSM Self-study Summary Report and Committee Reports, final 1999 LCME database submitted to the Site Visit Team (five volumes), chart of events for 2004-2006 accreditation process, 2006 final LCME Survey Report and accreditation decision, LCME publications and background documents, and final 2006 LCME database submitted to the Site Visit Team (five volumes).
  - Accreditation records, 2006 -- 2014; UA186.001.004 (Box 4)
    Contains TUSM resources (Student Handbook, Faculty Handbook, Guide to Third Year, and Electives for Fourth Year), 2005-2006; LCME materials from 2013-2014 accreditation process.
- Departmental annual reports, 1992 -- 2007; UA186.002; 2.4 Linear Feet
  This series contains annual reports submitted to the Dean by various School of Medicine departments.
  This series is arranged alphabetically by name of department.
  - Annual reports, A-M, 1992 -- 2007; UA186.002.005 (Box 5)
    Annual reports submitted to the Dean by the Departments of Anatomy and Cellular Biology, Anesthesiology, Biochemistry, Family Medicine and Community Health, Emergency Medicine, Medicine, and Molecular Biology and Microbiology.
  - Annual reports, N-T, 1992 -- 2007; UA186.002.006 (Box 6)
    Annual reports submitted to the Dean by the Departments of Nephrology, Neurology, Neuroscience, Neurosurgery, Obstetrics and Gynecology, Opthamology, Orthopaedics, Otolaryngology, Pathology, Pediatrics, Pharmacology and Experimental Therapeutics, Physiology, Psychiatry, Public Health and Family Medicine, and Tufts New England Medical Center/Tufts University School of Medicine.
- Meeting minutes, 1984 -- 2003; UA186.003; 1.2 Linear Feet
  This series includes minutes of the Board of Trustees, Committee on Committees, Executive Council, Faculty Affairs Committee, General Faculty, and Scientific Affairs Committee. Also included are meeting agendas and memos related to committee membership and structure.
  This series is arranged alphabetically by creator (committee, board, or council).
  75 years from the date of creation.
  - Meeting minutes, 1984 -- 2003; UA186.003.007 (Box 7)
    Minutes of the Board of Trustees (including Trustee Academic Affairs Committee, Administration and Finance Committee, and Executive Committee), 1984-2001; Committee on Committees, 1993-1994; Executive Council, 1998-2003; Faculty Affairs Committee, 1988-1994; General Faculty, 1994-2003; and Scientific Affairs Committee, 1990-1991.
    Also included are meeting agendas and memos related to committee membership and structure.
- Subject files, 1970 -- 2008; UA186.004; 3.6 Linear Feet
  This series is arranged alphabetically.
  - Subject files, A-M, 1970 -- 2008; UA186.004.008 (Box 8)
    Includes files on agreements with TUSM-affiliated hospitals; the Bingham Program; Clinical Study Unit; Deaconess; the Frank Stella painting "Bogoria," 1971; gifts and bequests; various foundations, trusts, and funding organizations; LCME accreditation studies and reports, 1991-1995; and marketing communications plan, 1999.
    The folder titled "Correspondence from Dr. Henry Banks's vertical file, 1980-1989" was retrieved by Eliot Wilczek, Records Manager, from discards of the Dr. Banks vertical files in the Health Sciences Library. Dr. Banks historically received records and documentation from the Office of the Dean for his research, and maintained a vertical file of topics.
  - Subject files, M-S, 1970 -- 2008; UA186.004.009 (Box 9)
    Includes files on the Mary Y. Lee Medical Education Research Day, 2008; MIT-Tufts; Morris Cynkin Prize in Biochemistry; National Fund for Medical Education; patent and copyright policy, 1975-1987; various foundations, trusts, and funding organizations; Pew programs; Porter Prize, 1998; Posner Hall; Sackler School; and various reports.
  - Subject files, S-W, 1970 -- 2008; UA186.004.010 (Box 10)
    Includes files on the Segal Lectureship; Singapore; strategic planning retreat, 2004; Maurice B. Strauss Professorship; Sweeney Scholarship; Sterling Drug, Inc. Visiting Professorship; Tufts Associated Health Plan; Tufts-MIT agreement; Tufts-NEMC Cancer Center; Veterans Affairs; the Veterinary School; and various foundations, trusts, and funding organizations.
- Additional accessions, 1970 -- 2013; UA186.005
  University records are closed for 20 years from the date of creation. Records older than 20 years that do not pertain to student education, staff and faculty employment and Board of Trustees records are open for research. This series may require review before it is available for use. Please contact DCA for further details.
  - Liaison Committee on Medical Education (LCME) Accreditation Records for the School of Medicine, 1999, 1996 -- 2000; UA186-004
  - Liaison Committee on Medical Education (LCME) Accreditation Records for the School of Medicine, 2006, 2000 -- 2006; UA186-005
  - Tufts Academic Health Information Network planning boards, 1970 -- 1980; UA186-011 (Box Large Map Case 1 Drawer 5)
  - Faculty Information Memo, 2009; UA186-015
  - Liaison Committee on Medical Education (LCME) accreditation records for the School of Medicine, 2013, UA186-016